[Music]
hello and welcome to the junkyard love
podcast
[Music]
at what age do we learn how to have
better conversations
at what age do we learn to have better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
what's up mermaid men this is barnacle
boy also known
as your host of the junkyard love
podcast jake rynes this is me
welcome i'm excited to have this episode
with ricky it was a great combo i love
catching up with ricky
such a great guy his energy is just
you're never not smiling when you're
talking to guy he's just awesome
lots of good info before we get going i
always love to start the podcast with a
little
chunk of info a little knowledge a
nugget of information that i have
stumbled across
or that i think is somehow relevant to
what's going on right now
typically it has nothing to do with the
guest or the conversation proceeding
it's just like a little contemplative
sound bite and so today i actually dug
up a poem of mine
and i gave it a little lo-fi vibe i put
on lo-fi in the background with some
rain noises and recorded it like so it
has this
effect um i mean maybe it's just gonna
sound
like a turd recording and i'm just
calling that lo-fi
but there you are anyway so this is a
contemplative
thought poem piece that i wrote i'm not
saying it's good
not saying that i'm a professional
writer but i am saying
it's something that i've done and here
it is enjoy
the contemplative thought poem and then
enjoyed the episode
with nikki nikki rick with
with i just got rick rolled with ricky
never ready
make it more perfect arrange a series of
events and preceding emotions
in a manner that lines up with the most
comfortable experience for the
participant
we want the maximum amount of fluent
feel-good
biochemical inner responses to our outer
environment
we hate discomfort a human being grows
through
pain change a new idea
a new experience a choice a choice to
grow towards the uncertain
or remain in the known
why is it that we do what we do why is
it that sometimes we're the same and
sometimes we're new
where within my body lies the soul and
is that me
if i never changed i'd still be an
infant how do my bones know to grow
why is there no room for my wisdom teeth
and shouldn't i be wise enough to know
are we sure we can understand evolution
as evolution evolution what is it
that all of humanity is growing towards
if love is the butterfly after our
cocoon of survival what
choice do any of us have but when
when do i grow the mind to correlate
with the body
in which way do i grow in which way
do i grow in which way do i grow
if i'm not my thoughts but rather the
observer what within me chooses to stay
or
go further i suppose i am
simply that i am i suppose i am
that i am
i always like writing everything down i
always have like anything and everything
i do i always
like everything like i have days of
notes
that whole over there that corner is
just like stacks and stacks of paper
i just because i do a lot of writing
yeah but i do a lot of um like while i
listen to podcasts and listen to stuff
i i take notes because it's not so much
that i'm gonna look at it later and like
study it or anything
it's a lot of the times it just helps me
actually stay focused on what i'm trying
to do
and like my brain remembers things like
so if something if i'm listening and
like
it's a neuroscientist and he says like
this cool thing about habit change i'll
like write that down
and so because it actually interested me
and it'll it'll help me
have one like almost anchor to remember
about that particular subject yeah so
it's
it's it's funny because note taking i
feel like a lot of times we're so used
to like school
like like oh you gotta take notes for
the test so you gotta turn it in or you
gotta
take notes so you don't fail the test uh
but it's like notes are just
a better way of kind of remembering
thing in the moment too like even if you
don't look at it later
yeah no i i completely i completely
agree because it's
like with
like shaken baby syndrome like my brain
like how i talk
and like how my brain don't communicate
with each other but with me
writing down something my brain
acknowledges it oh it clicks i'm
listening
but through speech or like trying to
like
uh talk about it i don't remember it as
well but when i write it down my brain
acknowledges it better
right so that's right there there's a
ton of there's a ton of science behind
that too
um i just i just bought a couple days
ago jim quick's
new book um
man it was on tip my tongue i thought
but jim quick um he's like a memory
expert he like trains a bunch of like
actors and stuff and like he's worked
with like presidents to like remember
speeches and
all these things he wrote about oh
limitless i think is the name of the
book
but um he talks about stuff like that
like different ways of taking notes
different ways of sometimes you can like
draw a line in the middle of a piece of
paper
and write like exact wording on the
right that you hear and on the left you
can write just kind of like your own
little
jot down little words that help you it's
like a cool little little hack
but um so rick and never eddie
or are you are you ready are you never
ready or
over i'm ready okay um
you were just talking about um we are
recording
you were just talking about shaken baby
syndrome so i want to talk about that
but i want
i would like to do before we go about
that um
i would like to talk about
weightlifting so i i want to i feel like
originally
we we had discussed i was thinking like
you have so much to offer the world um
in in the weightlifting view
of things like power lifting um all this
strong stuff
i i was talking to you about basically
someone who doesn't know anything about
weightlifting how can we get them
interested in it or somebody who
um like what are the aspects of it
what's like the brotherhood of it that
people may not understand those sort of
things so
um i guess we can we can
go back let's go back to where it all
began so
before the baby shaking syndrome before
the or
after that rather yeah um what got you
into weightlifting and then if you want
to do maybe a little bit of like
a bio when it comes to that too okay
um so start out
growing up just complete fat
piece of [__] just played video games do
nothing do what i want
pop-tarts in the morning like three or
four bags you know
mobile uh whole whole box of cereal
um just didn't do anything i just wasn't
driven because of the situation i was in
which we'll get in later
um and uh just free reign
but it's like high school you know you
start liking girls and like kind of
figure out stuff and
you know i was kind of morally obese
i would say like 2 30 at 5 11 but you
know
body index of like 30 uh percent
and uh i just wanted to change my
attitude as well
because i've seen you know in high
school you got different you know like
you got huntington and then cal women
coming together and you get to see
all those kids too and just kind of like
their attitudes and like
sports and i just kind of want to be
more like i don't know somebody just
kind of clicked in my head i just want
to be like
more active i want to be i want to uh
the physical appear and like
you you know you see those people you go
to the game you're like
holy [__] like you're just driven yeah
what was your sport football
football yeah football um
and uh i trained for that that yeah
football i wasn't the best
um uh
uh super like uh nearsighted
and i didn't wear glasses because i was
super embarrassed and i was already in
you know i was
fat this is like eighth to ninth grade
and uh i just didn't wear glasses and i
probably could have done a little better
if i would actually wear contacts or
something but
again my situation i just
didn't couldn't afford it yeah right and
uh but anyways
um so yeah just uh football like it
really
and then when i that ninth grade year
was at 20 2005 um
i did you know some double days at dog
days and
start practicing and got to know
everybody and super cool people and
uh mr hymes coach sunday um
coach phillips all those guys really
took initiative
of of me to get better and
uh and
i really wanted it so i just started
training every day running
uh ab routine um
i kind of just i kind of just jumped
right into it
yeah and that was pretty hard on my body
i would say my knees were
pretty wrecked my lower back but um
that shouldn't that doesn't have to be
for everybody like how i did it i just
was
i just wanted to change it i made it all
of a sudden but that's how i am
i want something i just i just dive
right into it right
with somebody's help or without
somebody's help um
and i would say
um for somebody like knew i would be
more like
getting into habits it's all about
habits
and like since i like for me since i was
doing it
since 2005 it became a habit what you
eat
how much i'm how am i how much i'm
supposed to eat um
it varies for everybody and how what
you're active or what you do for
a career um uh
if you sit down or if you're on ladders
all day and
you know carrying stuff or you're in
you're digging holes
for a living or in the heat or you're in
office all day
but anyways like for me uh i don't eat
super bunch on the weekends maybe
splurge have a go you don't need you
don't eat for four things of pop-tarts
in the morning anymore
no no i don't uh i was like 3 500
calories 300 but that's mostly like
ground beef rice and like eight servings
of vegetables a day
uh even more than that um it's about
balance
um what we used to know about the
periodic table
or the food table on that periodic table
um
uh it's way different 30 years ago to
now
and where like how much meat we're
supposed to eat versus vegetables and
whatnot and that's definitely something
to learn
um just knowing like what your fist like
a
piece of stick this size of your fist
and how many calories that is
um what's really fatty you know like
pork sausage versus
turkey sausage turkey sausage is amazing
you don't need to eat pork
you know have breakfast like of
champions of like pancakes
uh you know um 10 eggs and
10 sausages right you know what i mean
to get your day started
most of us like in the trades and
whatnot we don't even actually have
breakfast
it just if you think about it this is
another thing too like the carnival diet
or carnival a cart i can't even spray
now that's right
carnivore diet uh or fasting what not
most of those people don't eat in the
morning uh it's
being calorie deficient of uh throughout
the day
what not it helps it's just like
whatever can get you calorie deficient
and not eating
all these calories yeah i do fasting
every day myself yeah
do you understand like why people do it
why why they fast mostly in the morning
why why okay so 200 years ago
100 years ago most of us were farmers
and stuff like that we might have a
little
coffee wreck i mean the tiniest little
breakfast maybe
and we'll start work and then they have
a big like lunch was
their dinner you know it'll be just
three o'clock
and then they'd do some chores and go to
bed they might have another
meal and that that would be it they have
eight hours of pretty much eating
tops and they have maybe one big meal
one small meal
but in the morning you're getting milk
getting the eggs
you're hunting you're getting your food
you know we didn't have refrigerators
can just reach in and grab some food we
didn't we don't have we didn't have any
of that you don't have access to that
that's a whole different world yeah
exactly
and so
that's where the beginning of the
intermittent fasting for us
like became and then now it's like you
know
commercializing breakfast you know
they're trying everyone's trying to make
money
uh in the food industry yeah the food
guide pyramid i think was literally
kellogg's
like paid for it i think originally way
back it's like it's
[__] yeah it's [__] it's because grain
was like
sand like five or six servings or
something like that it was ridiculous
now it's like
one or two yeah we just know more is
another thing too like there's
it was kind of shitty but we also have
just learned way more about our bodies
and
yeah yeah no 100 percent and then um
trying everyone's trying to like was it
just these fad diets and whatnot and
you know it's whatever works for you um
it just you know not eating all these
calories so
um you know coffee is a good um
as a good source of like get up and go
um uh it you know suppresses your diet
or your your
your appetite and um just
uh something like that you don't need
sugar in the morning
um you know you don't i mean what you go
you i just can't stress it enough is
don't sit there eat a sugary bowl of
uh corn flakes and a bunch of sugar you
know what i mean i do i
so i used to be someone who like i was
like i love my cereal i gotta have at
least my cereal like i remember i would
like josh josh lozo would try to help me
out with a workout plan and i'm like
well i got to keep my cereal and he's
like all right fine
but like you know you're sacrificing
this thing later on but
now i realize i've i've experienced it
and i've like challenged myself
um with intermittent fasting like
because a lot of it is kind of like the
mental you're
you're kind of beating the mental at
first for anybody who's never tried the
fasting
it's like you wake up in the morning and
you just kind of habitually have your
bowl of cereal you habitually have your
whatever you know it's not
think about it too much but once you
start having that intent of like
the night before all right i'm gonna try
fasting tomorrow i'm gonna do fasting
tomorrow so you go to bed
you eat some good food um and then you
kind of start your clock at a certain
time
and for you just for me with fasting i
just say like all right i'm not eating
until
this time and if it's not that time i
don't eat so it's like your habit is to
walk to the
to the pantry and like pour yourself a
bowl of of frosted flakes or whatever
oh yeah but you what you do is instead
of choosing that mouth pleasure
you you build the resilience so it's
like oh okay that does sound good but
i'm going to try this fasting thing
and it it starts to like at first you're
like oh do i feel kind of crappy and
you're like
your body's like weirded out that you're
not feeding it sugar and so you're like
shaky or you're feeling kind of weird
but after a while it's like
your but your mind starts to like say
okay i guess i guess you know what
you're doing
like your body starts listening to your
mind rather um
yeah dude i think because i used to be
someone who was so obsessed with
breakfast and i was like i'm not giving
that up
but i really think that starting your
day without all that sugar man really
for me it helps a ton like whether
you're fasting or not even but just
bowls of cereal they're delicious but
you are choosing mouth pleasure over
you know your body functioning properly
i feel 100
it just slows it down like you're not as
productive in the morning
and um you know i don't
i don't condone for somebody that's
bigger or who's overweight because
they got hypoglycemic i mean they have
to have something to eat because they're
used to
the mouth pleasures all day every day so
if you just jump right into it it's not
going to work out for you
and take it slow yeah take it slow
because i mean
there's when you're big you're like you
got all kinds of health risks and
whatnot and
um it's just take it easy
you know getting habits that's all it is
you know go from two bowls of cereal to
one cereal a bowl of cereal
and tell your body you don't need it and
that's just what it comes down to
yeah you gotta tell yourself we're gonna
be okay yeah yeah yeah exactly
and then i said a good a good one to
help suppress it it's coffee
you can throw i mean you can throw a
little bit of creamer in it has a little
bit of sugar if you if you if
you know i like black coffee i'm fine
with that a little bit too yeah yeah
this is delicious thank you yeah of
course the old k-cup out there
um yeah so okay so you you said you've
always been a big guy but you've also
since i met you i mean i met you it was
definitely high school
because you were a year ahead you
graduated 0-9 yeah i was 2010. so
so i mean you've always been a strong
dude to me
like so do you remember so when you
first started lifting was that something
that you noticed like oh [__] i'm
actually like pretty strong like was
that
like oh yeah it was ridiculous did you
guys how [__] strong you really were
not really i've seen you lift some
plates bro well like at that time i was
just trying to lose weight so it's like
throw a sweater on throw you know have
have shorts on
two pairs of sweats throw a jacket over
and then go run
you know uh i don't think there's
anything uh
healthy about that at all but you know
again i was just jumping in it nobody
guided me right then we didn't really
have access to the internet way too well
you know we just got to dial up in 2005
or whatever it was
and uh you know i think our our high
school just got computers
you know yeah it was like in the library
and whatnot but i always reference
2007 is when the iphone came out did it
really yeah only
2007. only 13 years ago and our whole
life is ran by the damn thing now
yeah first like oh my gosh that's so
crazy yeah i didn't think about that
um but yeah so it's like trying to find
somebody to help mentor and
trying to get into place but there's a
lot of like fake people out there
like with their fake like their fat
diets um
like here slim fast you kidding me like
it's it's a quick weight loss but it
doesn't ingrain
anything into you a lot of most people
will gain
twice as much weight as they lost or at
least half at least half
i can say that happened to me not
exactly slim fast but
just trying to lose that weight quickly
you know you should be
you shouldn't be thinking 40 pounds in
one year you should be thinking about 40
pounds in
two years and losing 20 pounds and then
figure out
you know that's a solid like uh
just just slimming down getting a couple
hand sizes down
just figuring out how your body reacts
to diets and whatnot
not just jumping into them again have
somebody that can
place you where you need to be and then
kind of cut you back
right and uh you know um safely
especially when you get older or whatnot
jumping in diets it's just really hard
in your body and whatnot we're not
18 anymore and you could do you know 18
you can eat whatever
anything and everything you want if
you're just somewhat athletic
or busy pop-tarts yeah all the paw
patrol every pop tart in your home you
can eat
strawberry pop stars with milk
but yeah so um yeah i 100 stress that
get somebody that knows what they're
doing um
so so you you had found you had a couple
coaches that were kind of showing you a
few things like
we were talking about before the podcast
we're talking about even um
just like teachers that were helping you
out you know um
yeah in that sense so did you have
coaches that like kind of started
like they saw your interest that you're
interested in this thing and they kind
of teach you a thing or two of course we
have like weightlifting class in high
school and stuff but
yeah um yeah coach hymes definitely did
that
uh just showed me how to work out
properly and
he would go out of his way um to make
sure you know it spot me i asked him and
he would just sit there and spot me and
show me the right way to bench the right
way to squat and
to get at parallel don't quarter squat
uh it doesn't do anything for you but
hurt your knees
yeah um uh just all kinds of different
movements and sprints what they can do
for you and like
just the agility part of it too drills
um i a lot of people i just say you know
eat your meat and potato and whatnot and
uh that's just how it was though you
know just getting back to like
a paleo diet kind of thing you know what
i mean know what's in it if you don't
know what's in it don't eat it kind of
thing
meat potatoes kind of thing um
so i wouldn't say nobody really helped
me with the diet portion i just worked
my ass off
right and by the time i was sophomore
year i had a six-pack and i had a
six-pack
up until like 20 years old and then i
just
uh college happened and i ate a lot
yeah a lot but that was more like
started my powerlifting yeah
but you you kept lifting through that
because i know that we worked out a few
times together
i mean quite a few times together oh
yeah in that period i mean i was
definitely like i was always
because when i was in high school so in
10th grade i was like
probably 140 pounds i was just like a
skinny scrawny skater guy
yeah with those highlights with the
highlights and then the next day was red
hair
it was always something different um i
remember that but uh so
so for me when i started lifting started
lifting in 10th grade
um i graduated at 180
obviously i was like hitting puberty so
i'm just getting bigger anyway right but
um i gained a lot of weight and i was
lifting with you guys and i was just
like
dude i was always like super inspired
and super like i would always push
myself to that edge because i'm lifting
with these dudes i'm like
you guys are way [__] stronger than
me i don't know why you're lifting with
me but
i just i loved it dude you guys were
very um
like the camaraderie around like the
weightlifting crew
is very it's very cool so i like
skateboarding
i don't know so so i didn't do like a
lot of organized sports and i was never
super around like the fun friendly like
bantering
like that oh yeah like what's that ugly
you know like just like the the friendly
it's like it's all love for sure yeah
but like the
the just manly kind of homey bantering
and i feel like i started to get that
uh like more when i started doing
weightlifting like working out with all
you guys
yeah and stuff and it's it's it was this
cool like camaraderie
like you're excited to go to the gym
you're excited like even if you just
have headphones on for the whole time
the people there understand that they're
like like they're going to wave at you
they're going to say what's up they're
going to check on you like if you
if you've got like bad form or you need
help with something you just go ask them
it's
that's so cool um so
you so we had lifted together a bunch of
times but you hadn't started
competing until the more recent couple
years can you give me some of your
background on like competing like how
many how many
what is the official titles for like the
competitions that you do
um and then how many have you done so
far so
let me see that i actually got that
written down because it's been
three years just competing twice a year
um twice a year
anything more than that i just my joints
can't take it some people can do it more
um that keeps you pretty sane though
just twice a year
yeah i i like because there's so much
training like you gotta train in a
specific way like if you know
that at this meet i'm going to try to
accomplish this goal like you're
training 100
towards that in a different way than you
were last year for the other goals
yeah exactly and here's it
yeah so i went from a 600 pound squat to
705 in the past three years
um competing because i've been competing
since
yeah 20 2017 of august
uh actually when i met my first coach
cameron
um he was competing too he had his coach
and if you're gonna compete i think
everyone should have a coach or at least
somebody to
help guide him through the process
because there isn't
it's not just about the training it's
about the nutrition definitely
the sleep understand the mindset and
like get underneath the bar
that has your max wrap because
you see those guys squatting 1000 pounds
but that thousand pounds feels just like
you're squatting four hundred pounds you
know for your one rep max it's they're
they're under the same intensity
and like the same like the thought
process
everything they feel exactly the same as
you do you just get adapt
to the weight um anyways that was my
first uh
first meet exact actually at kabuki
strength
uh i think that was called uh regional
power lifting championships
and then we went on to oregon state
championships washington state
championships
and that's all uh uspa in uh
and then i went to apa um
apa is pretty fun um they're more
around the world usba started here over
here in the united states it's just
gaining popularity getting everywhere
else they're more
the raw i mean there's huge history how
everything's going on like they used to
be multiply guys wearing suits and stuff
like that
for many years and that um it kind of
died off in the
early 2000s and then we start going we
start seeing
uh raw
and uh from raw you know like bear bear
uh no nothing on your knees no belts no
nothing
that came kind of popular for a little
bit because crossfit start
gaining traction and did you ever just
fight those guys like the weight lifters
versus crossfaders oh yeah dude
you know what i i'm gonna be trying not
to be biased but
um you know uh you know it's whatever
you like doing but
crossfit i've never like uh the form you
guys got i'm sorry but
it's horrible it was so horrible like
i was like man ups or whatever they're
called like oh my god my shoulder would
blow out
right like it's like you know they're
standing they got
they got the pull-up bar right here and
they gotta like swing their legs really
hard bring their arms up and then push
up or whatever
i was like oh no that's no my shoulders
like you have to be 120
20 pounds 160 pounds to do that i don't
know
there's always like a friendly
competition like you know the if like in
the weightlifting world it's like kind
of a joke you make fun of the
crossfitter guys oh yes always or the
bodybuilders
like um
yeah i always definitely make fun of the
bodybuilders
no calf game yeah where's your legs bud
yeah um so so could you paint a picture
of someone who's never actually like
so someone who's probably even never
seen like on tv
like watched a meet yeah can you paint a
picture of how it is so it's like
okay so you're going in and you're
squatting 700 pounds what does that look
like so there's a coach
there's like there's judges and stuff so
it's what is it like it's just an open
gym room with a couple squat racks or
how does it go
yeah so that's the other aspect was i
was going to get as
like besides the coach the nutrition and
the mindset and whatnot
learning to be on the platform you got
three attempts
you got warm-ups for half hour to
hour maybe hour and a half tops
depending how many people are competing
there's different flights
there's women there's it's not just like
a woman flight and a men's flight it's
just weight classes
you know nine or 87 kilos
to or that's kind of uh yeah
um and like this every every flight to
different weight classes
and usually i lift with the big boys at
plus depending on how many people are
there again they divide the
flights up usually it's two or three but
anyways um
you gotta learn commands everyone has
commands like squat
you got your you got one squat rack you
might have two depending on how many
um judges they have usually it's one if
it's a
big me like 150 people uh or over 100
people
we might try to do two platforms uh at
once
in the platforms as in like squat racks
sometimes you have to walk it out
sometimes
you're on a monolift and all you do is
um you just stand up with it there's
little little hooks they
bring out and then you just squat in
place everyone's different um
i like walking it out it's a more
american thing to do
it's it's more it's more like like
russia what not
australia they have the monolith um
you'll see
um i don't know where that actually came
from
monolith but we we since the uspa
uh a lot of people weren't walking out
it's uh it's this is the it's
it's it takes way more out of you it's
it's there's more control
a lot more breathing bracing if you
don't do any of that you just you're
gonna
fold it's very is walking it out
basically a regular squat to where you
like you lift off the bars and take a
couple steps back or is walking it out
well yeah right right right where you
just okay okay you just you lift it up
you walk it you walk it back and you
squat
you can walk as many steps you want but
we all try to do the three-step
uh squat you just take lift it up
one foot back another foot back so um
but anyways uh so you gotta learn uh
commands
and those commands usually squat
everyone's a little different
most most time you'll see where
um you lift up or you lift up on the
weight
they have the coach have their hand up
they're not the coach but the
meat director or the head judge
whoever's in front of you
have their hand up and they'll like
squat
and you squat down and then you squat
back up there's no commander coming back
up
and just squat up and down and then when
you're uh
look like you're locked out they'll say
bring it in and that's it for the squat
but you have to make sure your knees are
locked out and your hips are
fully forward if it if you're doing this
weird like
half like if you look like you have so
it's called soft knees if you don't lock
out your knees
and uh uh they'll call you on it there's
three
and there's three judges the head the
head judge is always in front of you and
then you got your two judges
on your side always bench dead left
squat
and um yeah so you either get
a white flag or red flag if you got soft
knees and they all see it you got three
red flags you're
you know it doesn't count and it's kind
of it's a lot of
mental to on your first squat because i
think
squats mostly is a most anxiety
because you know if it falls on you like
a bench if it falls on you you got three
guys right there
ready to grab it squat if you fall oh i
mean got chains usually it's chains
um on a monolith on a like a usba rack
or a texas racker
um you walk it out and there's usually
they don't adjust the little bars so
usually the bars are all the way down
yeah they just forget because like
everyone's in the moment right
so that that's what if you bail out it
may not catch you and catch it in time
oh yeah i've seen it where like people
don't wear wrist wraps
for like gear gear is definitely
important like wrist wraps like keep you
nice and tight you know
you're here on your shoulders some
people like when you squat
and you're squatting low bar low bar
it's on your
rear delt your rotator cuff right above
it and makes a shelf
so if you have your elbow it's not
straight
up and down but little tilted 50 like a
15 degree
little tilt behind you creates a shelf
on your back so that's
you know so then the bar can stick to
you
um and then the wrist wraps help just
keep your hands in place where it
doesn't hurt your wrists and
you don't just you know uh your uh
elbows don't kick out and drop the bar
which that happens
a lot and you know it that
usually kicked out of a um competition
if you just bail out
runs the bar it's it's very unsafe i
mean nobody can catch 500 pounds
yeah you know especially if you're not i
mean we're all ready for it right there
our hands are
all on the weight but if it dumps like
you grab it the next person grabs it
like a second later then it's you know
yeah it's awkward it's too much weight
to be playing around with
yeah oh serious quick yeah exactly and
uh anyways
so you got three attempts with these
judges
squat bench deadlift on each one so you
get three
you only have three attempts i said
uh i already told you about the commands
on squad then bench
same thing you unrack it
they'll tell you down you come down
you touch your chest don't
you don't fold into your chest you got
to stop moving just
barely have right just just touching
those pecs
and they'll tell you to press and if you
look like you're moving under that bar
like
this or shimmying or um you're not under
control with that
uh that bar on your chest they will not
give you the
come up command they'll wait until they
see it so
if you come down super nice and gradual
and you touch that chest
most judges would tell you right up usba
there's some judges that don't
they'll make you sit there for a minute
or not a minute or two but a
couple of seconds just it feels like a
minute or two yeah exactly
and uh so then you press and then
they'll tell you to rack and that's when
you rack
some people just give you the down
command and press command and then you
just you rack yourself
it's a little different with um
different refrigerations
and then you got deadlift and again how
i said bench you get three attempts
just like the rest of them so deadlift
again three attempts
and then you
all they give you is you you grab that
bar they'll tell you when to come up
and uh um you pick it up whenever you're
you're comfortable you got a and uh you
got a minute
by the way yeah you're timed everyone's
time so as soon as they call your name
you got a minute
to come on the platform anyways
um on the deadlift the judge will tell
they'll tell you ahead of time like
they're just gonna have their hand up
and
until you lift it and then when they
feel like you're coming like you're
you dominated that way and you lift it
all the way up your hips are just like a
squat
knees locked hips uh forward
and um um like just straight up and down
your whole body is just nice spots
you're like you uh
and you're not slipping and you gotta
hold it for like a second or two
where you actually have a control of
that bar then they'll just
let their head down so it's down and
don't
you don't dump it you don't drop it you
go down with the weight make sure that
that bar
is on the ground uh if it's
uncontrollable they will actually call
you too
um but uh yeah that's so that's
that's the me and i said they can go on
for like four to eight hours
i've done one in uh oregon state
championship from downing
uh at newport for like i think we
started at eight in the morning and we
didn't end until eight so
twelve hours geez oh we were so tired
man yeah that's hard to like keep your
so what
so did you compete a couple times that
day like did you or were you kind of
waiting for your turn
so you always wait for your turn so it's
like it kind of i kind of hate that when
it's a bigger meet
yeah hard to keep that energy up all day
for me it
it is a lot of people like so if you've
been in the game for a while
they um they don't a lot of them don't
take caffeine
we take ammonia we hit they've got these
moaning capsules you know ones for
um to wake you up from like a first aid
you can buy
like 100 of them for like five bucks
and just each lift you just crack one
open and it just
jolts to your nerves and you get ready
to go helps you not pass out
i don't think it gives you a bunch of
adrenaline i don't think so i
it just shoots my nerves to keep me from
not passing out right that's that's what
it's mainly used for people use it more
like a mental thing
like it just it just gives you that over
the edge
attitude yeah that pump up before you're
about to grab 700 pounds off the ground
yeah exactly exactly so so it's squats
dead lifts and bench and that's what you
competed in it's those three that
yes yeah yeah and that's that's all
powerlifting
is uh you know it seems like other than
three attempts like how hard it can be
but the middle aspect of actually
prepping you got
the different phases you got 12 to 15
weeks uh if you're overweight then you
got to do
a water cut or try to gradually cut a
lot of people don't have control
as a power lifter you just shove
whatever's in your mouth
but i've always been the same weight
i've always well i take that back i'm
always between
235 to 260. my there's different weight
brackets just like wrestling
you got a 185 class 189
class 2 220
220 class 242 275
308 and then anything after that it's
super heavies um
and uh yeah uh i would say
uh i did the two for the 242 class
i've always done it i once competed at
two
uh 308s but i was that wasn't back in
college it was my first
uh meet which i didn't know nothing
about
yeah you were talking about how you like
went into it a little tired and
oh yeah i was you're because you were oh
electrician's stuff too yeah that was
the second one that's after
i was so the first one was in college
and i didn't know nothing about it and i
quit
weightlifting because i was telling you
i went to i was trying to go to psu
and that didn't happen so i had to go
work
that that fell through and i start
working so i quit
powerlifting i just worked out gradually
and
uh lost a bunch of weight like 45 pounds
to where i'm now and uh but that fir
that second one which was the ramp up
um of my uh what am i uh what i'm at
today is
uh yeah i was tired and oh yeah that was
a lot of hours and
very stressed out yeah very stressed out
yeah so did you so okay so
you've been weightlifting for a while
now so
way back when let's go ahead and rewind
it because you know it actually kind of
almost catches me off guard when you
said baby shaking syndrome i don't think
i really knew that
i don't i don't think i knew that about
you oh a lot of a lot of people do it
yeah they they they get i guess get a
little hint because
i can't control it like sometimes i
drool a little bit i just i just can't
control like some emotions
um uh or stumble with my words or how i
talk
like i'm really good with my hands my
brain and my hands work really well
together it's just
my vocabulary and how i stumble words
it's not because like
i didn't it wouldn't
call it like i went to speech therapy
and all that stuff
as a little kid and a lot of it uh hours
and hours
hours of it and i just didn't
didn't help because of just what's wrong
with uh what happened with
me as a child and uh
that came down to oh like
i was like less than like six months old
and i was in cal
we were living in california me my
brother between brother george
and we you know my dad he uh
abused us physically
um and uh gave us uh shaken baby
syndrome
um our uh hepatoglobin to the uh to the
brain just
your br uh your blade uh your brain
bleeding and swelling
and uh they take
in that process to relieve it they just
take big old needles and just
back then i don't know now um just big
needles in the back of the head and
just try to relieve that pressure it's
you know it's just
water it's just all water because your
brain is just with water and
the membrane and whatnot around it um
and uh
literally just big needles and um
yeah just to relieve the pressure and i
my brain
relieved uh he'll just
uh you know fine afterwards but with
some damage
uh my brother he had actually had a tube
inserted
um a shunt um in the back of his head
and it actually drained it was the tube
that went from becca's head to
his neck down to his stomach they had it
implanted
yeah so like and with that like you
outgrow it
some people die but most people don't i
mean it's a very
minut number and uh your
your brain will actually grow around it
and will just
just kind of smush it and it's it's
there it doesn't hurt yeah
crazy but again it
affects your learning ability because
that brain damage is such
such a young you know you haven't your
brain all the fibers and everything
haven't
uh your frontal lobe like none of it's
really developed you know
um and we couldn't walk until we were
almost four like six months before like
preschool
yeah uh it was crazy like i got pictures
of like i look like i have an alien head
yeah yeah it's crazy i was like what
that's like no that's not me
like mom was like yeah that's you but
my mom didn't know it was my dad until
i don't know i don't know how exactly it
happened he blamed it on the babysitter
and back then but this happened a lot
though
like it was just kind of swept under the
table where people didn't talk about
being their kids
it happened you know now we got child
abuse we got
um social services and all kind you know
all kinds of stuff and uh but 30 years
ago no
no we didn't it's different yeah they
just started fighting out about
this kind of cases in the 90s like when
they actually started digging into again
uh uh services for it it wasn't until
the 90s
that i know of and yeah and then i don't
know how my mom found out and as soon as
she did she just packed up and
left for washington with me and my
brother without my dad knowing like he
went to work and
we left yeah just literally packed up a
u-haul whatever we can
left the house he got the house and
moved up here with family
and been up here ever since i have
yeah i mean you've always like since
i've met you since we were way back in
high school you've always been like
friendly humble you always seem pretty
smart to me it's it's weird
like i mean i guess like if you talk
about it you're like oh i stumble over
my words or i
sometimes whatever i mean i think for me
i'm
like i have i guess adhd um and i like
i've
i did okay in school but i kind of had
like learning just like i just i didn't
understand things the way that other
people did i just had to get there on it
in a different way um but you know even
now
i get better and better from the podcast
and just having conversations but i
stumble over my words and like
i get distracted or like down these like
streams of like
not the the content i was trying to talk
about or whatever
um but you know it's funny i feel like
the more people you meet
the more different types of people you
meet the more you like talk about
people's story
the more you i don't know you you start
seeing
like i guess what i'm trying to say is
like i never really noticed that you've
stumbled over your words like i
like it you seem like you're a normal
dude like it's not like it's like really
a hindrance i mean i'm sure you've dealt
with so i don't mean to downplay i'm
sure you've dealt with like
so much and and gone through so much
work to like make it better and stuff
but
um it's it's it's interesting like we
all just kind of have our own
our own like upbringing in our own like
um
there's different like labels like like
adhd or
um you have depression you have anxiety
or you have like you actually
have like physical like you were damaged
in your brain when you were younger
um but it's i don't know it's just great
that you don't really like let it
identify you like you you're just
a normal nice friendly guy and you seem
pretty damn smart to me every time we
hung out
oh thanks man yeah of course um
no i completely agree um you know uh
every situation is different it's just
how you take it emotionally and mentally
like just
um and like what you do with it that's
what it comes to is
every situation you don't you you don't
know everyone's situation
but but you can see it you know everyone
ha
you know we all have like like was it
you only have so many emotions but it's
not hard to see it on your face you know
what i mean you walk around
um with the sad face and how you see
somebody somebody said hi oh hi
you know how's your day you know you
somebody doesn't
say how their day really is we just say
we're okay right you know what i mean
so um it just uh but
you can still see it on the face but
nobody asks nobody asks
how you're you know what's going on in
your life or you know
like but you know but again that's we
have our own past and we
choose to deal with deal with it how we
want and
the way we want and then put the people
around us
of how we act right where do you think
that came from in you like
how where do you think like your
optimism and your i mean because you
have like some rough things growing up
yeah and you've remained an optimist
about it uh
seeing the [__] up people around me
excuse me excuse my language but
really [__] up people yeah my mom's in
drugs uh
got worse after like uh
just like she start having episodes
like well we don't have any mental
health uh
mental health like problems in my family
at all and it's
it's usually derived from a parent or
some sort but
everyone's sound of mind um you know
everyone gets pressed or whatever
however you want to label it you know
everyone everything's getting a label
these days
but i think it's just a bunch of meds
and freaking somebody's making money
yeah i'm just sure but i mean everyone
but everyone has these feelings and
whatnot
it's how you control them what makes a
difference um but anyways
um but just seeing the shitty people
like everyone doing drugs
luckily i didn't really see anybody ever
really do drugs i'd find it
or see the aftermath of people
like slumped over or crashed for like
three or four days on my couch
i'm like i don't even know who this guy
is it just smells like incense in here
yeah like instead they always burn
incense when they're smoking mass so
it's like my mom would open the door and
i needed something as a little kid and i
was like it smelled kind of funky i like
cat piss but it was incense
yeah is that lavender cactus yeah or
something yeah that's what i just smell
in my house i'm like we don't even have
a cat
i was like what the [__] i didn't
understand i was really blinded to it
until
i was like 12 or 13 to be honest like i
didn't know what i was looking at you
know we weren't you know we went through
what uh
the only thing we go through is a dare
oh right
yeah in sixth grade or fifth grade for
some people but
um but even then they don't tell you
what drugs look like they don't tell you
what the symptoms are that i remember
they just say you know
you know be drug free you know be
positive all this stuff
and uh they don't show you real
real world stuff right and i was in it
and i didn't understand that was in it
and the people around it like everyone
was affected by it
yeah i mean it's i can't imagine it's
such a complicated thing like
who in your life would explain to you as
a kid
like anything about drugs that would
like be beneficial i mean it's not like
you know it's not like your parents or
your mom in that situation is gonna like
be able to give you the right lens on
those sort of things
no she was in my sister wasn't it uh
uh everyone everyone boyfriend like
everyone like my sister boyfriends
my mom's boyfriends um
luckily my mom didn't bring a bunch of
like random like boyfriends over
um excuse me
um but yeah i just didn't bring a bunch
of
boyfriends over she had one main one but
he was
super deep into it both super unstable
not going good for each other i mean
domestic there was domestic there too
and i saw that that was scary he was a
big guy he was like 250
six two six three just big guy it was
always a labor labor referee
roofer framer kind of guy um
he seemed like he could be such a cool
dude but he just got
they just put people around them that
just done drugs they just lived
i mean my mom's such a like such a nice
lady
but she just allowed people to come
around that
because she wanted friends she didn't
like being lonely and me and my brother
were gone most of the time
school and uh sports that's when it got
really like when me and my brother start
going away from the home
she just got really bad because she she
just put herself around people that
weren't good
and uh you know we lost we we lost our
home
we rented a house over an alpha drive
and yeah we lost that because
her boyfriend didn't pay the rent and we
lost it
and she couldn't and she already spent
money that she didn't have
yeah you know those fast cash places
where you can get a lot of credit real
quick you know
lots of interest oh yeah no bro she's
i'm pretty sure i said i love my mom but
i'm pretty sure when she dies
the credit card companies are coming
after me like there's you know what i
mean
like hundreds of thousands of dollars
there's there's no
there's no getting away from it i don't
know yeah well i sincerely hope that
doesn't happen i hope there's some sort
of
protection for you in within that i
don't know if there is but
life insurance but i don't know if i i
really don't talk to her i don't know if
she has life's insurance that's that's
literally that's why people get life
insurance because the cover you know
the funeral and everything else but
nobody really thinks about you know
nobody wants to think about dying
and it's so crazy because i so my dad
got into meth when i was younger
um i the thing about me is i never had
really formed much of a
relationship with him before that like i
was i was like probably nine or
something
yeah when he got into it but his he came
through it not through
loneliness as much as it was pain his
was arthritis
i feel like it a lot of it is kind of
like a lot of my driving factor to like
be so
like holistically healthy like i've
always worked out been active
i'm always trying to like um like oh
you've got a rash on your foot is it
because
you ate the incorrect thing well let's
learn about that you know it's always
trying to like solve
the body problems and i feel like a lot
of it is because um
you know i grew up in it like my father
wasn't able to solve like why he was in
pain and he would just go to doctors
you know that's what you think you're
supposed to do is just like i'm in pain
i go to the doctor and they fix me
and we don't we don't really think of
like preventative maintenance we don't
think of like how is my
food affecting me how is my um you know
like how can i strengthen these areas
like with with my physical body like but
he was in a lot of pain so
he got into drugs through that um
and i have like a few years of of kind
of
chaos um but
you know it's
it's it's it's interesting it's because
because it is all love like
you know we're still trying to work out
our relationship you know it's like i
don't have like a bunch of like
bitterness towards
towards my parents um it's it's
interesting like as you get older as
you're like man you're like oh okay like
these things happened
like but here's how i got to reframe
them now like here's what i learned from
them
here's what i am holding on to or not
holding on to
you know it's it's like a tough healing
thing oh yeah i i completely agree yeah
and
creates love though did you with that
like that process
like i didn't i didn't i didn't revolt
against it like i just let it be
like for me um i didn't like go rebel or
anything
do you in your situation do you think
kind of revolted like
nephew parents like i mean i've always
been kind of i've always loved i've
been attracted that punk rock rebel like
i feel like when we met i was probably
like
like dressed as an emo dressed as like a
punk rock guy like i always just
i also though so my i don't think mine
was super shaped by like the trauma
side of like my dad doing meth and like
we lost all the house and like
mom heart broke like but i was like once
he started doing that it like
it did break us a lot but i feel like a
lot more of my like rebellion
was more just because even before that
even before the traumatic like drugs and
stuff at home
um i always felt that i was just way
different than everybody around me like
i always felt like out like the black
sheep of the family i was like
really really that and i felt like i
kind of felt
like the black sheep of like every
situation like i just felt so
different than everyone yeah so i think
after a while i just like
embraced it and i liked that like i
always
i liked seeing like like when it comes
to fashion anyway like so i like seeing
like in a music video
like some the lead singer is wearing
like those pants and i want to be like
oh man i could wear those pants
like nobody else around me is wearing
those nobody else has even seen those
pants before
so um and then as far as like rebelling
um i was always
i was like a good smart ass like i was i
would i would kind of like [__] up or
like we're trespassing skateboarding but
then i'd be good at like
kind of like sweet talking the cops or
sweet talking the the teacher to get
myself out of it like that sort of thing
like i was kind of like
um like a rebellious manipulator in a
sense or something
but um yeah i mean but it created
i i did hold on to a lot of resentment a
lot of um
like misplaced anger you know but over
the last few years like i
uncovered that stuff and i'm like okay i
could reframe this in this different way
but
it was never like
i don't know it was never like holding
on to to a hate of like
like you did this to me and like he's
staying it's like i never want to stay
in that victim role like
like i feel like just we grow out of
that victim role and we kind of channel
that energy
into new knowledge and like i know what
i don't want to do i know
i can look at people who are in that
situation or people who grew up around
that same situation with a lot more
compassion
like i can see them for what's really
going on yeah
no i complete yeah 100 i and we all go
through the same process
i think you know we are in a different
situation
but we all go through yeah it's the same
process like the grieving and like
[__] this [__] that and then like the
rebellion
like uh you know and you're you're
always gonna be different when you're in
a situation of like
uh drama or you lose something
you're on your own situation but you
have to develop from it
and how you said you're you're you know
the past couple years you've been in a
really good place you've been doing your
own thing
you're able to situate everything going
around you
and whatnot and you can get grasp of
this and grab that and actually really
develop from that
but you know what's shitty is that a lot
of us are just stuck we're
stuck where we're at uh mentally
i wouldn't say me i'm i'm right i'm
right with you know how you're saying
like kind of situated in like
especially the past like 10 years i
think it's been really development but
some people aren't able to do that
because they're just stuck because they
didn't have anybody reach out and
tell them hey you can do something else
you don't have to do this
right you know it's just what you know
you know what i mean
it's just it's just what you know and
you can't
um and you don't know how to get out of
it until you really [__] up and tell you
you know you got a court a couple of
times and a couple do you ask me a
misdemeanor because you're [__]
possessing drugs not saying that's what
i have but i'm just saying i've
seen many situations like that and
they're just stuck in a system and when
you're in a system
you know what you're you're uh labeled
you're definitely labeled uh like for me
i've been to jail a couple times
i'll say it uh you can't because you
pulled your pants down in witches
no or maryville
no that was a good time though uh
you want so you've been you've been to
jail a couple times though
yeah it's sealed you guys can't see your
[__] but i've been in trouble
um yeah i've been i've been i've been in
trouble um
it just because it just it was my
rebellion like i just i
went to jail a couple times um
uh not gonna bring out what that was
about but
it was just like me rebellion um it was
just me trying to grow
and i just didn't understand which way
to push and
it was like i had a good mindset but
then i'd
[__] up and then i actually i actually
got kicked out of school for like six
months
um out of high school mm-hmm oh [__]
yeah
that was my sophomore year uh big rubble
um but i was able to be able to
still go to um what was it called
um this uh program they had for
troubled kids like i had like cindy
oliver roscoe worley
i only had those names for a while i
know i had those guys i had a couple
other kids in there too
um but um but i was still able to do my
credits and stuff and have my homework
handed through that program and then i
was able to sit down once twice a week
or twice
no was it every other day or something
like that to go to this class
um mr moe uh ran it i don't know if he's
still alive or not he was pretty old
when he was running it
super awesome guy super he he
he could teach you anything and uh he
understood our situations
and uh he was strict when he when he
needed to be
and uh he helped he helped my situation
now he actually really steered me
towards a better light um
but uh yeah and then after i came back i
was pretty
uh helped me out a lot i
still had my credits i still graduated
with
more than enough uh gradually like
high school like a 2.8 i was able to go
you know go to college
do you think the uh like just think so
so like in your life you didn't really
have
like role models as like you know you
didn't have anybody and until
so your parents anyway of course you
know they weren't role models they teach
you things
retrospectively later on in life you can
be like okay i don't want to do this or
i do want to do this or
you know my mom was hurting because of
this dad was hurting because of this
whatever it is
um but those role models that you did
have like i feel like
the more that i grow up the more that i
look back in a lot with this podcast i'm
kind of like
i'm always mining different people like
for me i'm mining friends i'm mining
like co-workers i'm mining like the
managers and mining like these people
that i meet like
for information like what are they what
are they teaching you at all times
um and i feel like a lot of us don't
realize it but we don't really have
role models that we look up to like even
if your parents don't know
that much and you like okay well um my
parents didn't teach me very much i've
never really had a good role model so i
don't really know what to do
well you're also like watching a lot of
tv you're watching movies like you
we're everything that we're consuming is
kind of like influencing us
in these ways yeah and i think that um
for me like you realize
you realize a little more
retrospectively but like my friends
parents like my parents weren't there
for me but like
when i would go to my friend's parents
house like the little bits of
information that like
you know my friend emily her dad would
like say something to me in a certain
way when i was 16 or 17
and it literally was probably one of the
most profound things that i learned like
i never had any older grown like adult
person
say something like that like teach me
about responsibility or teach me about
like
caring about one another or uh you know
even manners like those sort of things
i think there's a lot of people who
didn't have role models but they think
they feel stuck maybe in in that they
think like well this is how my life was
and this is how i am but for me
you know you can look at all these
different people that you meet your
friends as parents your coaches
your your workout partners your homies
like there's little things that
everybody's teaching you at all times
and
even me i would go last couple years i
would start to kind of find like
what do i you know i was kind of
searching for this like father role
model thing i think
in a sense and so i started finding guys
like jordan peterson and tony robbins
and
um and just like these people who are
like inspiring and like teaching and joe
rogan and stuff on
on online yeah yeah and i almost like
would kind of picture them as like a
little bit of a father figure like what
can i learn from this person like if he
was my dad and he was teaching this to
me that he's talking
like how would i take that differently
and i think that i think that you
like you kind of did that similar thing
like you started having coaches and
people in your life
pop up and you were willing to like
listen to them and like do
you know try what they said and and
they're like hey ricky if you do this
this way you can have this opportunity
yeah and you started listening
i think a lot of people don't
we we identify ourself
with the position of being stuck a lot
of times yeah
the vic that's where the victim the
victim role comes from you know
that goes right back to there and then
from there you know you can sprout or
not do nothing you
stay in the same situation and a lot of
people like sticking in their situations
not like
but they don't know what to do because
they didn't have me and you get older
and you know i'm like am i going to talk
to a four-year-old what to do about
their life
not really you know it just it's just
not common
you know it's they're 40 years old they
should know by now kind of you know that
kind of mindset
but being those you know uh those
listeners that are younger is like
find somebody that you know as well is
willing to listen to your story but also
help
teach um what's going on um around you
you know financially like school doesn't
teach you financially they teach you
half crap history
math's awesome always and then language
you know
um and you know you don't get taught and
it's this if you really want to get down
the rabbit hole you got the system
you know uh and then uh stuck on tv i
mean
uh you know watching stuff like mtv
music and stuff like that how you're
saying like
watching the music videos and like you
know like influence
yeah yeah exactly how it works exactly
and then you know
um just uh you're like oh i want that
but the thing is
like it's just all i just all um
just the whole spectrum of like i think
crap you know
you don't get to find out who you are
you see what however other people are
living that
i want to see it not attainable but
those people are you know
making millions of dollars just because
they're feeding you content right and so
right so they're going to feed you
whoever gives them the money to
feed you you know the content um
and um yeah i you know it's
uh i'm not gonna say it's the easiest
thing to find those people who influence
you or
um but it's but it's a little more easy
i think actually it's a little more
easier because now we have the internet
uh we you can siphon siphon through
people like
talking about what they're talking about
and what other people are talking about
what that person talked about like you
know like oh the fed
oh so this other thing so
um you know over youtube you got
youtubers and stuff like that they
yeah somebody talked about some certain
content and then
another youtuber would say this person's
wrong because of this this
that you know there's and they just kind
of youtube back and forth and whatnot
you can see and then they actually have
to show their um
credibility you know what i mean and if
you don't then it's like
don't don't listen to them like if you
have no credibility do not listen to
them i'm not talking about being famous
i'm talking about actual like
um studies uh some scholars study
something you know
even though it's like a hundred and
something pages just for the intro of a
scholar study
at least read the the um
uh intro of it at least understand or
just something you need to get the grasp
of
what you're talking about you know it's
the same thing for like
uh weightlifting like um like knowing
every aspect of that and like how
like i train i need to know things but i
don't know everything so i get coaches i
pay
i'm you know i i pay people to help me
and i'm in this in the place to do that
you know uh
not everyone's going to do it this kind
of stuff for free or
for you know immediately 50 bucks or you
know whatever it's
they're they had to work their brains to
get there right and to teach you
so you know you gotta pay to play kind
of thing um
but uh and uh you know and then when you
get to a certain level um in your
thinking process or
you know it's the same thing with school
like i i like school as a learning curve
like college high school are from 18
and below 18 to preschool or whatever
you want to say
i think it's all [__] i think we're just
going in and out or just
whatever but as soon as i hit college i
got help to get in college
um that expanded my mind i was able to i
had to
maintain my own schedule i didn't have
somebody telling me
i can make it want i can work i put my
work where you know i can
i could i manage it myself i had it i
paid
to be there and i had to learn if i
didn't then
um it didn't it showed me more like
management skills
they actually gave you real world real
world
um skills you can use
anything any class you want you don't
have to get a degree you can just get go
there just to see if you like it
most people like you know none of us
like schooling because of school
i just taught a [__] we had to be there
i don't know how many hours anymore
eight hours
at a time every monday through friday
and then
um get taught a lot of [__] i'm not
saying all about [__] like i like
what's her name war miss world mrs
warwick
i think that's her name the little do
you remember the business ladies uh
super short five like five two hard
hearing i feel like i'm picturing
someone in my head but i don't think
that ever happened oh i think that's her
last name
but anyways like computer skills she
talked like business manage
or not businessmen like business uh like
write letters emails how to actually
socialize in like the business world and
stuff like that like that wasn't
that was a core class that was awesome
yeah that's a good class to know yeah it
was
but that you know those are you know two
thousand
five house said like 2007's when iphone
came out
you know what i mean that you're saying
and uh
uh you know we're all entering uh just
trying to figure out different aspects
um of what's going on in our lives and
uh
but anyways um yeah just
in your situations where we're at in
life is where we put it
you know even though we don't know much
this is where we're at and we have to
learn from that situation we have to be
more open-minded
about what's going on and oh sorry we're
good
um i'm gonna turn that off
sorry about that are you good yeah i
mean so dude i think that's an important
thing to point out
is like i talk about awareness i used to
try to use that word often on the
podcast like
you know it's it's kind of like if you
want to use just a dramatic example like
the 12-step program for addicts
um or like alcohol anonymous or
something like the first step is a
meeting you have a problem we've all
heard that right yeah but
um it's so cheesy but it's but it's it's
it's this truth of like
it's not so much that you have a problem
or that you're like you have to now
identify with this thing
it's like once you can admit that you
don't [__] know everything
you can realize where you're at like you
can you could be willing to ask for help
you can be like okay this is what i
don't know here's what i need to know
you can be open to someone actually
teaching it to you yeah okay
like i feel like a lot of us you know
with social media
we have this like highlight reel that we
post we have this like
our best selfs like our our
hopefully everybody thinks i'm perfect
in these ways sort of things the social
media kind of like gets our brains going
like that
yeah and yeah i think people buy new
cars the houses
the uh boats right which is which is
is so awesome it's so cool but i think
that we also have to remind ourselves
that that is not all what life is like
life is also
like they had bills that they had to get
through they had like some college that
they had to get through to get the
skills to where they can afford those
cars all these things like
we just we decouple um
we decouple ourselves and so we almost
feel like ashamed almost
of like admitting like man i don't know
[__] so i really need you to explain
that again
like that sort of thing i think but it's
to be humble and to be
and to come out any situation like i'm
as a non-know-it-all
you know like just as an open like i'm
ready to be taught
yeah you have to yeah 100 and i
man i can't but 16
18 years old 19 right after you know 18
after high school
i think we're all lost and uh um
and knowing or emitting you know how you
said first step
um like in the 12 steps it's like
admitting that you're lost and how
you're saying like just
but get in the right direction
um is the hard part yeah definitely um
because i took like for me i've took in
multiple careers i've done
like the college thing i graduated i
didn't do what i wanted to do
um because of the situation of going in
the country at that time in 2012
with a black shooting with a white cop
and
uh and all and that uh how that uh
escalated in this country um so i didn't
become that and then work in the mills
and then that wasn't for me you know
just figuring out life but it was like
10 years
like eight years no yeah 10 years later
figuring out this is what i actually
want to do and like to be an electrician
and but it took me that long been
several different people to kind of
point me the direction or at least just
talking
that who were successful right even
though
it was hard like you know when you reach
out to somebody yeah who is successful
um and they ignore you doesn't mean
they're ignoring you like they don't
want to talk to you they're just
a lot of people are super busy right
they're just working they're just
working grinding
just just just just grinding
and um
and going through the situation you know
they're going through situations like
like i'm finally like for me for
instance like i was
ever since i was 20 years old i've been
saved like working and saving saving and
saving
getting through bills going through
college paying off everything
um just finding that job that would give
me
where i want and that's all um
and liking my job too is
uh i don't that's
let me see how to explain that um but
just yeah liking your job making that
money that you feel
comfortable enough to be financially set
and working through it
and working through that process of
managing money managing bills managing
time to yourself that's a big one too
you can't just work
like i was i was telling telling you
earlier before the podcast is uh
i would work 13 days on and one day off
and then do it again
back to back doing that divorce schedule
at that
georgia georgia pacific mill um and work
in
overtime we would only work eights but
most of us get dead overtime
because we were just one you know making
that money and that's
you know we're already there eight hours
um
so might as well just work a little more
and make a little bit more money
and that you know working uh working
that divorce schedule
dangling that carrot right in front of
you yeah i know but it wasn't you know
making 25 an hour and
making you know doing a little over time
making 80 thousand dollars a year
was a lot you know it was that i knew i
wanted eighty thousand dollars or plus
and i want and work less but working on
a mill i couldn't do that i couldn't
work less
um i could do it probably in like 10
years from there going up to paper
machines but i understood that
i wanted more time to myself my mental
health wasn't good like i
i broke down a couple of times i'm gonna
i'll admit i'll
i broke down a couple times when i was
drinking or something i just break down
because i was just like
i didn't know myself at that time like
yeah cool i had all this money
but i was like super broken down like
mentally
because when you go to work you just
you're there you're the you know for me
when i'm at work i'm at work i don't
think about anything else but after work
then it comes
then it comes down on myself because
then i had to have this dude
this dude and i haven't reached i
haven't talked to this person i've seen
on social media
my friends mom died this person's going
you know you know
people throw up stuff on there it's not
all you know it's not all glamour
well instagram you don't see that on
instagram right right it's just pictures
and happy smiles but facebook you know
you'll see some drama and stuff like
that and like some people talk about
their
somebody die or they're seeing their
grandma for the last time
and i just couldn't be there for a lot
of good friends and i
lost a lot of good friends too but i
made a lot of good friends too because
i changed my uh
my career in the mills i just
again i said i wanted a certain amount
of money i knew what kind of lifestyle i
wanted
and to pay my bills and what i wanted
and uh so i got up and that's
you know became an electrician um
and i love i love the job there's a lot
of theory to it there's a lot of
schooling um you know you can either go
to like perry
perry tech for like two years and spend
a
half load of money and uh try to pay
that off in the next 10 years afterwards
or
you go union hall um
the ibw or non-union which that's why i
went with the jtc
apply there uh it's a little easier
there's a lot of kids
there's uh getting a high school um
that don't have any work ethic at all
like
um so i
with i don't know how to explain that um
like a lot of kids coming out of high
school there's and there's older guys
too there's like 40 year olds
going through the apprenticeship and
there's a lot of kids or just kids and
they just [__] off in class
stupid super stupid but um
and they're but they're we're all going
through um
this program and it's four years um
that bw is five years um
uh we all make really good money
uh i i just and we're all like most
most of the people in the trade who are
younger uh
all coexist we're all friendly we're all
learning we're all learning we're all
like you're constantly like lecture like
anything like technology-wise is always
developing
right right like that's exciting
actually i feel like yeah
it is but keeping on top of it like
there's so many people we have to hire
to do let me see next uh to do like
controls and stuff because we don't
usually jobs
yeah especially jobs like fire alarm
systems we have
people just for that we have people just
for um
running uh hvac systems and stuff like
that we'll run the wire and
run the pipe and hook this up drill this
into an hvac system throw a probe in
to communicate to the system the uh
to the yeah to the system to to tell
you know a thermostat you know or at 85
it needs to be at 85 keep on going until
you hit 85.
but um yeah i just always um
just always evolving and what not but we
you know we can't
not one person keep up with it and we
have to hire out for
multiple people so it can be a little
stressful but it's as soon as you got
those people
you know you figured out this is the
person i need for this and this isn't
what not like you gotta run jobs you
gotta it's a little stressful
uh i haven't ran a job yet i do uh i do
some like little things
by myself you know we do as an
apprentice you do
you have you know they expect you first
year you're grunt you're running pipe
you're
uh pulling wire second year you're
trying you're still you're
figuring out theory like what a what a
neutral does what a ground does like
or like how if you get shocked or if
some
like the risk of getting shocked which
that happens a lot or you get
um um loaded neutral from like a cash
register
uh shocks you that sucks so like all
like specialty equipment like all this
the neutrals there's back feed from it
because there's
i can't i've written out a relay but uh
not a condenser i can't remember exactly
what it's called but anyways it allows
so much voltage to be tooken at that
time
and whatever's extra from the 120 come
in
uh feeds through the neutral back to
right um
it goes it always goes back to the
original source of power yeah so it
takes what it needs then it what it
doesn't need it
returns it to the ground right uh
neutral so neutral so neutral ground
technically you know if you really look
at it neutral and ground are the same
thing because if you look in a panel
that's the main main disconnect panel
the main panel not a sub panel
the neutral and ground are tied together
they're bonded together with a wire
so it's like so
i just never understood why the ground
and well i do now because of the back
feed because then
you know on the neutral you can get
shocked on the ground you can't it just
that's
helps for at least amount of resistance
to not get shocked the ground is there
and it goes back to
um goes back to the source of power so
it doesn't go through you it goes
it goes through the ground instead yes
especially especially if the piece of
equipment is grounded
yeah it has to be if it's not grounded
so you're like you're in a
a panel no let's say you're in a um a
foursquare box
and it's a junction box and you're
working on wires and whatnot you
actually hit the
hot wire against the four square
i've done it a couple times accidentally
but um and
instead of shocking you it goes through
the box
which box is grounded through the box
being grounded
uh goes back to the and that's the path
of
least resistance which will then allow
it to
not go through you and go back to the
source of power
right so that's how that works dude
electricity is so it's
it's like daunting it's always been like
this scary thing i remember
i shocked my i was like i was a teenager
at some time and i was actually helping
like like help paint the interior of a
house or something i forgot exactly what
it was but i was
taking off like the tape on a wire and i
remember like putting my finger inside
there on accident oh no i slipped or
something and i shocked myself
and like from then i was like god damn
it dude electricity it's
not like so i'm always like reluctant
about it i've been i learned more and
more and obviously through my audio
engineering degree i had to like
crash course it um oh yeah i remember
just off top of my head
um one interesting fact that i learned
like
more recently and i feel like i've said
it so many times throughout my life the
term electrocuted means that you
died from the shock it means that you
it's like we say like oh i got
electrocuted and like apparently that's
improper because the term electrocuted
means that you died from electricity
really
shocked it means that you were like
shocked from it oh okay
i mean i i'm pretty sure that that's
right i i remember it being like a
mind-blowing fact when i
yeah yeah huh well
the english language is pretty out there
just saying compared to
like spanish or any yeah super we're
no there's words yeah there's so much
slang too like it's like especially
nowadays with
with the internet and stuff like there's
so much sling and crossover and like
this word means this but it also means
this
and it means this if you're in this area
and it's it's just complicated um
i wanted to ask you about something i
was thinking about this morning i was
listening to like this neuroscience
podcast about this guy who was a
skateboarder
and he didn't have a lot of structure
growing up and i was
it sparked me because i was like oh i
guess like if i think about it i
actually didn't really have like much of
any structure
myself um and it's something that now as
like trying to like
run my own like program business corner
of like what i'm trying to create here
like a lot of what i come up against is
like trying to create structure for
myself like i'm always trying to like
get my plans going i'm always trying to
like all right what do i need to do
tomorrow like what do i um as someone
who
like it's likely that you didn't have
very much structure growing up
either do you find it like as as an
adult now do you find
like like relief in structure almost
like almost like
um you know like if you are bad at like
organizing yourself but you join say the
military like they've got it all
mapped out for you you know what to do
at what time it's almost like a relief
almost um how do you do with structure
do you feel like
that's what something you've had to like
discover or like find on your own now
yeah i think so i um like
again like in high school or middle
school or elementary i just didn't
have that even though they try to teach
it you know you go to this class
at this time you at you know on this
period and you know they kind of go
through it and like they talk about
notes and stuff but
until it's real-world kind of stuff you
know school was a joke i i
i just didn't i literally didn't learn
anything i was just i was kind of slow
but i mean college i just literally
learned everything i could write a 20
page essay i got like in english 102 i
i got like an a and i was like and that
was
[__] hard um but i was like i
but i i taught myself that structure
like i was like i had to i was like it
was real
i'm paying for this this is what i want
and like to understand stuff like
note taking and how we were talking
earlier you know you might take notes
and like just to help learn
but you might not look at it later but
you under you know you you read it you
heard it you wrote it down it just
multiple different neuro pathways to of
learning that study or
or just learning whatever you're you're
learning or even your daily
uh what you got to do you write down
you're like and then
see like i was telling you earlier like
since i have like shaken baby syndrome
um i have trouble like
um yeah like talking back and forth like
trying to keep like a conversation in
one place
like obviously you guys could probably
tell a little bit but
um i
learn better with my hands so when i'm
writing some down or texting
or like i got it's called notes on on an
android
galaxy s10 i i've been have i've had
this notes for like
um at least seven years at least like
since the first
galaxy i've had and uh i uh
write everything down like today like i
wrote down a bunch of notes
just to just kind of keep my my mind
focused for today
and my to-do list um my jobs like even
when like day-to-day at my work
we have to do this i'll ask my four man
like what do we need to do
then i can and then if we're running
conduit and
pulling wire and making up or demoing
stuff and like trying to figure out home
runs and
trying to do uh trying to get our job
done for the day like i will write a
quick list on break you know or right
before we start i just write a quick
list like okay you wanted this this this
and that and uh like um but yeah how it
today like just had a whole
it all mapped out and then after this i
have it all mapped out
um yeah like tomorrow i even have it all
mapped
i haven't mapped it it's like i have
notes so you just like take a few i mean
i'm sure it's just a natural thing that
doesn't even take you very long now i'm
sure
just you pull out your phone and kind of
jot down like oh here's some key points
that i want to remember
during this podcast here's some key
points that i want to
make sure i remember like don't fickle
around when it comes to this next job
like so it's it's you know i think we
we've been like in school way back in
high school and stuff it's like oh note
taking oh i want to take no it's almost
like uh
the teacher's making me do it so we pay
attention to this movie sort of thing
yeah but i think when you get older in
life it's like
dude like find what way what like learn
how you learn
i think that's one of the most important
things i feel like you've done that
pretty well man like just
taking notes for me um in my creative
endeavors
i'm someone who like i think it's
something
it's it's a little rambunctious but it's
something that i feel like i have to
hold on to i kind of have this thing
where
i like thinking my all my ideas are
great
as in i like thinking that like oh i had
this creative idea i had this one line
for a poem randomly in the middle of a
tuesday as i'm like trying to eat lunch
like i like telling myself like maybe
that is really good
but let's not overthink it right now
because you got the real world you're
trying to solve this
like you don't have a bunch of time to
just daydream right now about this cool
idea you have
so i write it down on my notes i write
that first line of poetry i write that
idea for a dj mix i write that like um
like writing prompt that i want to
explore later and i
jot it down as a creative i just jot it
down to my notes and i put my phone
right back in my pocket and i returned
to the present moment
yeah so that's that's kind of how i use
my notes um
and i but and then so a lot of times
what i do for podcasts too
is uh i'd have a piece of paper and i'll
write like bullet points like
10 things five things whatever just
whatever kind of pops into my mind
um and i don't even have to like really
read it during the podcast like a lot of
times i'll just have it
once i wrote it down it's there and now
it's kind of fresh in my mind and those
are kind of
in your brain remembers you know you got
to give your brain a little benefit of
doubt like sometimes you might stand
there and like look at the wall for four
seconds and you're going to be like
but nobody cares man like it's like for
me
like when i'm talking on a podcast for
example i know that my guest isn't going
to matter if i like stumble over my
words like
i know he's not going to care if i'm
like let me kind of remember what to
talk
you know my brain's looking for that
thing like just give your brain a second
i think we get hard on ourselves
like i know me like um it's probably
stemmed a lot from
like i was the youngest of four kids
like before
before that so i i imagine that like
getting that word in was really
difficult for me like trying to
get my voice heard get like my opinion
out or whatever was probably stomped out
being the youngest of four kids
yeah so um a lot of times i find myself
trying to like rush through or like talk
too fast or try to like
make sure i don't say the wrong word or
whatever but
a lot of times you just slow down say
what you're at like
and the stuff the little notes that you
took earlier like they're gonna populate
you know just give it a sec just give it
a little breather for me and
i feel like you do that pretty well too
so yeah
you know from thinking about what you're
talking about and like
you do this and that and this and that
like because you're
you know your entertainment your
technician and whatnot and
like you're just getting pulled this way
and that way like thought process like i
just like
like very it has to be very creative you
know what i mean
and like and it's so round
uh round um gosh i can't even talk i'm
so jacked up on this cat
i heard i already had like two or three
cups before i got here oh man this is my
second cup dude
um but uh you're still like just
everything just
going and going and just like i don't
know i just i just
if because sometimes i get like that and
i just can't go to sleep
like my brain like just goes and i just
couldn't imagine
like you know it's your job like you
know you know
that's your job and like i just couldn't
sleep yeah i like i'd be i might get
like five hours of sleep
yeah i mean i've i learned to work with
it it's kind of this funny thing i
almost have to like
uh it's like like i'm like on or off a
lot of the times like it like
i've got to like
i mean it's kind of thing like like for
an artist like imagine imagine you're
like a
singer and you have like this music
video and like the music you know
we've seen these videos some of them are
just like they'll make you cry it's like
this incredible piece of art you know
but like in order to to communicate that
properly
it's not just like following these
things it's like the creator the person
behind the scenes the singer the one
writing songs one make the video
whatever
they have to like they have to get there
like they have to like push themselves
to that emotional level they have to
like
they have to lock in on that emotion
that they're trying to express to the
world
and it's a it's it's it's a and but then
you also have to
like you got to be a creator and like
push your mind in these crazy insane
ways but then also like sometimes
15 minutes later you got to go sit down
at a dinner table and you got to be
professional with a tie on
you know what i mean sometimes it's hard
like
um sometimes i'll be here for like uh
like quarantine for example
i was i didn't see anybody for like
weeks and weeks i'm
if not a month like yeah she comes home
from work but
um i remember going to i was just in
this creative like
i was doing well it's creating and
drawing and doodling and making music
and playing piano whatever all my
creative [__] yeah yeah and then uh
i remember i went to the weed store and
i walked in and i literally just like
like a robot i was like uh
i like just said my order i was like uh
a quarter flower indica
this price range and i like said it and
i was like oh my god i'm sorry dude hi
how are you
i'm sorry i haven't talked to somebody
for a while yeah because yeah we get in
these different like mental states and
i bet you that you have that a lot when
it comes to like working out like i
always think of like those post
interview videos of like
ufc fights and then like they
interviewed the dude who got who got
beat up and they're like so how do you
feel and he's like
what he's trying to like formulate his
words after like a
ufc fight yeah it always seems crazy so
do you ever have um
when you're when you're powerlifting
like do you ever have to like get there
like i mean
i know you're talking about like you
guys you guys um sniff pneumonia or that
yeah yeah yeah and then um do you also
like
do you listen like slayer and [__]
before you yeah like you get there
well so it's so different like if i'm
really gonna get there it's something
like
kind of sad it's it's i was like dude
yourself bro it is like deep like
obviously
wait wait you listen to sad music oh
yeah oh i love that
that sucks i could send you some
playlists that i run to i love running
the sad music
[Music]
oops that's the one no that's not the
one that's the great that's grand
uh great advanced fleet i was listening
that right before i got here
um no it's like i don't know i dig deep
like really like house of just that
mental aspect of that like the sport
like i take it more than a hobby it's my
lifestyle it's like i chose
like i chose to do this i'm not going to
be in this sport very long because i'm
just getting older and
journeying out next year and it takes a
lot of your time like hours so you take
you're training for two to three hours
so now i'm not talking about just
sitting there bullshitting you're just
you're going i tried not to talk to
anybody but yeah you're in the zone
when i'm actually in prep i lose between
like two
like 20 to 40 pounds i get in my weight
class
um uh i don't care about looks like i
might have a ripped six-pack but i don't
care
that's not what i'm going for i need to
be in my weight class i need to be in
that weight class i'm going to be strong
i need to be well fed there's nothing
uh non-nutrition there's no donuts going
in
there's there's just street beef
vegetables rice
some uh brown rice
like just kind of cut it up it's super
plain most of the time
because we're in the trades we're out
and about we don't have microwaves i
mean food cold i mean rice
and barbecue sauce and hamburger and
vegetables cold
like it's just there's no microwave i
haven't had a microwave in
uh at this job uh for at least two or
three months
so when i have come home i'm like yeah
no no chicken no chicken
i don't i don't believe in chicken at
all for
for at least powerlifting if you're in
bodybuilding you want to get that that
lean in but we're not i'm not about lean
i'm the beef the beef has
uh more iron more calories uh
if you get some 937 or um or you can go
to matt's meets
uh and get whatever like what kind of
like the
uh leanness of the beef you want or
you can you don't even have to have any
fat it could be 100
beef which i don't it doesn't cook very
well you got to have some fat to cook in
it but
um just the nutrition like you talk to
any of these like
uh bodybuilders and stuff like a lot of
them like are switching to beef
um super lean unless it's like right
there at the show and they have a short
prep they'll switch to chicken
okay so i lifted for a long time
um but i don't think that i super had
like much of like a mind body connection
like i would a lot of times i would go
in and lift
um like granted like so even when i was
like extremely depressed and extremely
like sad
i would go in and i would still lift
pretty much every day but a lot of times
mine would almost be like this like
reinstalling my armor or something like
it's kind of hard to like conceptualize
but
like i would go in for that pump like
i'd take pre-workout i'd go in
and like i want to just i want to look
big and i want to look tough out when i
leave
that was something like i loved and and
you know that's cool like you know
sometimes those are great those are
great days sometimes you just like i
want to
i'm feeling a little weak and i want to
be a strong guy today and it's going to
make it feel more confident sometimes
that's cool
but um i think that i was missing out on
a lot of like the mind-body connection
and now with my little skinny yoga body
i i um i don't know what you're laughing
at because we could arm wrestle i mean
i'll take you off those guns bro you
better watch out uh
no but uh i you know the mind body
connection like it's
it's uh for me it's like a little more
in-depth it's more of like a spiritual
thing when it comes to yoga but
i think like any mind-body connection
anybody working out
is kind of a you know what however you
typically use the word but like it's
kind of a spiritual like
center thing like it's really you're
connecting to like your soul and you're
like
your your body is like pushing the edge
of its limits but you have this little
voice that you're like no no you can go
farther
that's kind of like the like the you
that you want to feed right
yeah yeah it's all mental it really is
could you could you
can you talk like i don't know just just
anybody who's working out in whatever
way they work out where they're just
starting to work out they've never
worked out but they want to try
like what do you what do you think about
like that mind
body connection like what does that mean
to you
oh yeah so i would say
just kind of how you're talking about
like understanding like the contraction
the eccentric
the um eccentric movements of your
muscles
and understanding like when you squat
like i have to understand everything
when i'm out of the bar like how to
brace how to walk out how
how i like to just send like knees
forward first or if i'm squatting in
like and that's in like knee wraps or
like i need to understand every aspect
of that movement if i don't then i'm
going to not hit death
or i'm going to fail i understand like
um i got just every point of it like
just to make that lift and but it's the
same thing when you're going like as a
newbie and
like you're just you're just there like
you know you pick up a weight and just
start crawling
oh you know understand that whole
movement and like like what
you know the bicep has two heads like
which portion of the head
are you working your quads just
you know you got a different section of
your quads and like
when you're doing a um uh leg extension
for your quads uh understanding like
toes in toes out and point you know
toeing just pointing back and like how
it hits the quad differently or squat
like you do a [__] squat on a vertical
press
versus a little bit wider and like what
you're hitting you're hitting more
glutes and ass or you're hitting more
quads
um just like the whole aspect of that
movement and uh
that's how you really develop uh muscle
and how you actually
really burn calories you know if you're
just in there just getting a pump real
quick and get in and out you're not
doing [__] for yourself that's just more
oh excuse me um that's more like eagle
lifting
and whatnot and that's how you get hurt
100 that's how you start getting hurt
you start just
throwing you know throwing random weight
every week
versus like getting programmed or like
looking at like uh the conjunctive uh
uh training or like west side barbell
like they have like there's so many
templates out there just to kind of
show you and there's so many videos
there's a lot of good videos out there
i'm just
i'm just showing how to really get that
muscle mind connection and to work those
muscles
yeah so yeah it's just uh um
when you get to that point though and
you can actually you'll feel it
like your muscle growing and like the
pump
that's when the pump comes is when you
really just feel you know you feel that
curl that
uh bench press you know bench press is a
compound movement
or a squat and it's uh you can't just
it's super hard to fill
for uh that my
mind and muscle connection so as a new
lifter i'd
recommend more like uh like just
doing like flies of some sort or uh
dig it away from uh or like free weights
of like the curling or the tricep just
like single worm just like feeling the
muscle
yeah slow movements um
um don't sit there in between sets and
[__] the whole time and you will
if you're doing what i'm talking about
and you're sitting there bullshitting
the whole time and you're texting on
your phone
you're not going to feel any of this um
you're going to sit there and
look like you're doing no work versus
sitting there for 10 seconds and really
feeling it versus blasting it through a
workout
uh for 10 seconds right it just yeah
it just that's what that's what it comes
down to though is just
um i mean especially your weight loss
goal like when you run you feel like you
know you're
you're feeling like your hands are here
you're feeling the movement
you know you're going forward and or
you're running upstairs you know
you gotta uh feeling each each uh
each uh stairs or when you run up the
stairs or anything i just um
uh it just just really feeling what what
you're doing and i just go in there with
the mindset of
i'm here just i'm here to work out i'm
in and out and
um just you know get in there and have a
mindset and i guarantee your
workouts are going to be ha uh half the
time
just as much work every time
because i will work out two to three
hours
uh and i won't sit there and [__]
but i can tell you i'm i'm tired
but i'm doing what you know i'm feeling
every workout um
getting everything out of it what i can
because if you just go in there half
house you
you got to do is twice as twice as long
or three times as long
to get where you want to go right so
understanding
uh what actually like the uh
physically and mentally what what you're
doing is is
key yeah yeah yeah that's that that's
the other side of it besides nutrition
yeah dude i agree connecting to that
the mental it's like like you can't just
have your head in the clouds like
thinking about all these things and
trying to ruminate trying to solve all
these other problems while you're like
doing doing a bicep curl like you know
maybe there's some times where you just
want to get moving your body while
you're doing something else sure that's
cool but
i think like giving yourself that time
like how you say like try not to
[__] i think
what people could take from take away
from that is like definitely try not to
[__] but like what if you when
you're working out you put your phone on
do not disturb like if somebody texts
you like what if you just don't respond
if someone emails you what if you just
don't respond
like what if you don't ever check social
media in between your reps like
try to try to be centered like when
you're when you're resting like maybe
as a listener maybe you can you can try
to like think about
why am i here like i'm doing good like
like power yourself up
think about your next rep be like
feeling your body you know and you were
saying run up the stairs like
there's kind of this like imagine being
super tired like you're oh like you're
kind of clumping like oh it's so
exhausting
you're just kind of peeling yourself so
like instead of
i don't like let myself get to this when
i'm dragging my body like if i feel that
i'm dragging my body or i'm kind of like
limp running or whatever i try to remind
myself mentally like
oh yeah you're working out let's let's
go let's give it your your all let's
find your edge and i'll
straighten my posture i'll be like okay
where do i feel this yeah my legs are
sore but like
could i flex my abs a little bit more
could i could i kind of
put my mental focus on my core as i'm
running and maybe that'll help me get a
little bit more of a well-rounded
workout
yeah just basically like being here for
your workout
is something that you know
often a lot of times and it works
sometimes
i think it is beneficial but on it but
not every time is
putting something in your headphones and
like floating away like daydreaming
about whatever you can while you're
while you're working and like that's
great and a lot of times it gives you
that pump up but
there is this like mind-body connection
that sometimes you can miss out on like
there's
for me like i was saying i would kind of
do the ego lifting like i would go in
and just get that pump and i would feel
good
and a lot of times it was that was like
my armor like i was like
i felt um you know i felt like i had
like a strong snail or turtle shell
around me
you know if if you're feeling all pumped
and lift and whatever but
i don't know man that that connection
that like hey this is my body and like i
want to take care of my body and i want
to explore
my body and i'm allowed to explore my
body this this um
this like i always
i think that the way that we look at
like weight loss or like okay i have a
vacation coming up so i want to get
shredded
because we're always thinking about you
were saying you don't really like care
about your body looks it's like oh if i
if my lifts get me to have a six-pack
and that's just a symptom that's just
what happens that's just working yeah
that's just this is the product of what
all right done yeah it's something it's
not something that you're going for and
i think
i think a lot of people i mean speaking
from my lens of someone who's been
working out i've been working out since
the 10th grade
i was working out i'm a huge advocate
for people with like depression and
anxiety and those sort of things to work
out
i was i had depression and anxiety but i
was and i was still working out
and i think that the the way that i was
working out
the like the ego workout
was actually like harming me a little
more than anything like i could have
been
and now i have you know i'm not like i
have
i have weights out in the gym or in in
the garage and stuff and like i'm still
going to work out and i still
i like doing cardio i like doing yoga i
like doing anything active
um but i've just it's it's a different
way of working out now like
so when i go back into the gym it's not
so much like
staring in the mirror like trying to
just visualize big guns it's like
i'm feeling this connection like i'm
pushing all corners of my feet firmly
into the ground
i'm trying to like really watch my
posture best i can you know even if
you're just doing a bicep curls
yeah i think um and you know there's all
these different variations of it like
you
you lock in like you you got your
headphones on and you're like i'm not
having
the [__] sessions like i'm here to
work i'm here to accomplish my goals
i'm here to push my body yeah yeah no i
100 percent and then the other aspect is
how you're saying like your heart you
kind of harm yourself because you're
just
there for ego and whatnot and
and that that a lot of people do it's an
outlet and whatnot to get away
but also you know people [__] but
uh but more mentally though is uh
just it really affects how you look
on life because you see like a lot of
people cocky they're like pumped
up and like just more of a shield like
you know you're just walking they're
like
like it's like the uh uh no lat syndrome
you know people are just walking around
like this and like what's going on it's
like
but you know there's more going on there
and it
a lot of people don't realize and um and
or is a relief you go in there just to
relieve yourself a little bit aggression
um and whatnot and then you know if you
were going to throw a little spin on it
it's
this whole covet thing dude like
a lot of people are went nuts
because they didn't have an outlet or uh
just or to go work out why not like i
know somewhere i know a lot of people
did and they tried to go
you know they tried to go hiking and
they got closed and then all these state
parks and everything and then they just
didn't have an outlet and you got people
had to go see um like counselors and
like get on meds and they just and they
start drinking more
you know there's people i mean it's in
the newspapers yeah like people like you
know
over you know drink too much kill their
liver you know dehydrated themselves and
um um they just they really had to deal
with
what's going on with themselves and uh
because they didn't have an outlet and
uh it messed a lot of people up
right and uh oh man
yeah because i i mean i got there i mean
luckily i was able to lift
still but not on occasion like i like to
and i still
i mean i but for me i already dealt with
a lot of things but it was able
like it was more for me for an outlet of
dealing with more other stuff
around me i had more time for what's
going on
which i was lucky to have an opportunity
to
to have yeah i i think that anybody like
you know hey
listener if you like any way that you
can get into the gym like don't go
go don't go thinking that now you know i
suggested these things like really try
to connect with your mind body
don't go thinking that just because you
don't really know what that means means
that you're not ready for the gym like
whatever gets you in there whatever gets
you started working out
and then you can you know you talk to
the people uh you get some advice you
can start reading on reddit you can
start reading on forums
start like learning a little bit that's
the thing you know this podcast
knowledge is power it's
it's like the more you kind of like
let yourself dive into these things the
more you can learn about it and how it
could affect you you know
channeling that energy like i'm someone
who's like a very go
you know i'm usually pretty go go go um
i have this like energy that i've got
like channel into an activity like
whether it's creativity or like
sometimes i gotta run because i'm just
feeling like too antsy yeah
um find that thing but then you know
while you're doing it just
listen or just try to uh try to like be
present like what am what am i
doing here like what am i as as you're
running as you're working out say what
you know what
what do i want out of this like is it
just am i just protecting this arm i'm
just trying to get this armor
and if that's the case that's okay
that's where you're at yeah you know go
from there but as someone who
you know that you talk about that armor
for me man it's like it
rings so loud to me because i was the
skinny guy
who was out on his own when he was when
he was very young
yeah and so my protection like i
literally
i would be walking home from school or
walking to school or walking to work and
i get beat up
like so to not get beat up anymore i'm
gonna
hit some weight so you're not gonna [__]
with me i'm gonna get tattoos so you're
not gonna [__] with me
that was kind of like a lot of my
personality was built off of a lot of
that
and i think now i have
you know i'm 28 now and i
um i don't know i don't lift as much but
i just have like this connection to my
body i don't
i don't use it as this like armor you
know
yes you look way more healthier i would
say like four years ago
you're trying on at on the on the pounds
you were
but you were doing all this other stuff
too you know you're just trying to get
in just to get out
i remember that i know i was longer than
that [__] i can't remember exactly but
i just remember that and you're start
traveling for work um
you look so tired coming in and you're
trying to come in like every day
and that's i don't know i didn't like
giving myself breaks i didn't like
taking a day off you know that wasn't
good
yeah you're gonna rest yeah exactly and
um but
now like you you look you found that
that mean uh just of in between like
work
uh acting you know actually working your
brain and then
working out like it doesn't have to be
there like you're counting it every time
it's
you're going you know you're feeling
what's going on and you're getting the
workout and
you know you get done you don't need to
sit there for you don't need to be it
doesn't need to be more than a half hour
it really doesn't and you know don't be
discouraged when you first start
like uh i got a good example um my
girlfriend rachel
she got into weightlifting she's been
active she's always been active always
go to gym she's just be a planet and
fitness kind of person
nothing against platinum fitness it's
just commercial and pizza and [__]
but um uh
[__] fatties edit that out
um but anyways uh she uh she was really
discouraged i had her meal prep like i
showed her how to meal prep and it
showed her what calories like what
actually
like empty calories were what actual
calories were and empties like
like eating skittles skittles is just
fast sugars uh
shoot up your insulin and make you gain
a bunch of weight like that's that's
what quick triggers do but i'm not gonna
get too much into that but um what i'm
trying to get to is
i just showed her a routine so i kind of
get her working out and like feeling
that
feeling her work out and like how to
push it a little bit and
push it as in like what your body can
actually do because
for a person that likes to read that
sits that does customer service
and like just like you know it's not
like a labor intensive job
um so you didn't get you know you don't
get to work out your body like that and
understand limits
so i showed her what her what limits
were
and when to hit it and when not to hit
it as in like
you know so you're not fatigued you know
how you you're going in every day and
you look
so tired but you didn't but you went in
there because you know that's
your armor and whatnot um but underst
and then
you having somebody like show you limits
and like you don't have to push it six
days a week you really don't you don't
need to be in 60 days a week you don't
you really don't
unless you're eating garbage every day
but i was showing a meal prep like i got
a
showed her all these meal preps i've
been able to preference since i was uh
20 years old 20
22 years old every day i have every week
every sunday or every friday i meal prep
have all my meals done but i'm showing
what maintain uh like maintenance is
what how to gain
cal you know gain muscle and lose fat
you can do that if you're a little bit
overweight and whatnot if you're more
skinny person
you shouldn't be losing weight but you
know that's where
like high protein um
um so much carbs and whatnot give you
enough energy to make sure you get
through your day and your workout
and having a little extra carbs when you
work out
um but anyways i showed her all this and
like she was discouraged
at first she didn't lose weight she
actually gained weight
but that was just uh because uh
you start getting water weight and stuff
and like you're stressing your body out
working out stressing your body out
so you might not see uh you know you
lose weight she actually gained i think
like 10 pounds
super discouraging and she did yeah i
had her
look at the scale every day that's not
for everybody but for her where her
mental state was she need
she needed that uh constant
reminder what she's doing you know yeah
just having something that you know your
goal she wanted to lose a little bit of
weight
uh uh because she's stressed eat
she was stress eating so i showed her
the what uh i bought a scale and had her
weigh herself every day so then she
understands the level of like stress
someday she'll gain like two pounds
or some days she would lose like three
or four but she understood where she was
at and you know
i might had you know i'm not with her 24
7 that right be weird but um
[__] psycho uh
but i i showed her what she needed to do
and
she did what she wanted to but then she
got more refined she asked quite you
know you want to be
cognitive to talking to
whoever or looking up whatever like
understanding like
what empty calories are nutrition or
like like a lot of people in the
northwest were
vitamin d deficient iron deficient we
don't eat enough like meat or like
like nice whole like whole grain
vegetables we don't eat enough if
anything so we're
like super deficient of everything
because we're on the go go go
and uh um but it took
like after i got her to a routine she
understood
well routine is not put you know she
pushed herself just enough
where the next day she still can go in
and not be tired
and uh if she had like a two day break
she would push it that day do squats
go run two miles under 15 minutes which
is nuts for a girl
dude it's crazy she can run that i was
like
what no dude most officers they're like
their pt has to be like it's a mile and
a half under 15.
she can do two miles under 15. or right
at 15.
um uh yeah it was
it's just crazy but like but she she got
it's she's been and we went there for
like two years
almost two years and about six months in
our relationship she wanted to change
she saw what i was doing and she wanted
to change
her habits um but yeah
i said it's overall she finally
understood like how she's working her
body
what she's feeling and if she's
overfeeling or she got hurt she'll take
a couple days off it's nothing you won't
lose your gains or you won't gain a
bunch of weight just like this whole
kobe thing a lot of gyms are down
you know as long as you keep to a
regular schedule of
like your food and or intermittent
fasting or um
uh uh letting your energy and other
things you know you guys could run you
guys can hike you know we're in the
northwest and
you can do it you can do anything and
everything you literally can i mean
active
yeah there's there's so much like i
that's what i do like for actual
recovery i get out we
um i i just get out um
yeah like yesterday we uh walked the
whole beach of like cannon beach
yesterday
like just active recovery like i'm
totally big into that that's
that's a whole that's a whole different
discussion but you know
i got out and it was moving my body if
you just sit
you're not doing anything for yourself
you're really you're not you're sitting
on
your phone or staring at the tv and
neither of those two
are good for you at all there's like
there's nothing healthy about it there's
mentally and physically yeah i think you
know
i think yeah that's that's well put
ricky i i think that
just getting something like getting
moving getting like where like you know
we're talking about if you do this then
do that and if you're at this level then
do that like
something to remember is just like it's
your body and just
figure out where you're at with it just
learn about it just feel it like
go work out go run go stretch and like
find your edges like oh this feels good
when i do that it doesn't feel good when
i do this
oh i feel a lot better after i do this
like yeah cool follow that and then
you'll start stumbling into like
you'll meet people who will suggest new
things you'll you'll be around people
who like do different kind of workouts
and you'll be oh yeah okay
i've done a few months of this now i
kind of want to try that there's nothing
wrong with
with it you know like definitely follow
your bliss when it comes to that and
another thing that i always emphasize on
this podcast is [__] stretch
stretch dude and and i'm not just saying
like stretch right before your workouts
i'm just saying
like every day like don't it doesn't
have to be like a elaborate like hard
workout stretch thing for me i just
think there's some days if i don't have
the intention
to to do so i'll like wake up
and get right to my you know um like
like get right to my chair here and just
sit and you work for hours like
some people say you're a receptionist or
something like you wake up and you kind
of drag feet and
whatever and you go sit at work and you
go sit all day and then at home
you watch tv whatever yeah in between
that if you could find some time to like
when you wake up just do ten minutes of
stretching five minutes of stretching
like move
movement and and i think i think breath
work is
not even just a complicated breath work
but just oh try to notice am i breathing
from my diaphragm am i breathing out of
my mouth moving out my nose like
just stretching and breathing around
getting that movement i think
is a good start i mean if somebody's
never done any sort of workout
yeah no 100 percent yeah and uh yeah
just don't stay staggered guys
yeah don't stay sad um ricky
it's been a pleasure my man i really
appreciate you coming on the podcast and
teaching me a thing or two
no problem man thanks for having me yeah
you bet man we'll have to do this again
sometime heck yeah
yeah listeners get in that gym lift some
weights drink some water and take care
of yourself
later
you